Finding aid for the Alma Hawkins papers, 1919-1998 LSC.2182
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alma Hawkins papers
1919-1998
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hawkins, Alma M.
LSC.2182
21.8 Linear Feet (32 boxes, 8 flat storage boxes, 4 record cartons)
This collection contains the professional and personal files of Alma Hawkins, the creator and original chair of the UCLA Dance Department; faculty member at UCLA, George Williams College, and Santa Monica College; and practicing dance therapist.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audio and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
RESTRICTED ACCESS: Use of audio and moving image material requires production of listening and viewing copies.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Linda Gold, 2013.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9975427973606533
Biography/History
Alma Hawkins (1904-1998) was a pioneering dance administrator and educator who wrote a number of books about dance education and composition. Hawkins helped to establish the field of dance therapy, and founded the nation's first autonomous university dance department at UCLA.
Hawkins was born in the rural town of Rolla, Missouri, daughter of a dairy man and a homemaker. Having no outlets or training for dance, her early interests as a young girl were in athletics. With the help of her high school basketball coach, Hawkins was able to attend the University of Missouri, where she majored in physical education and received her first exposure to interpretive, folk, and social dancing.
Upon graduating in 1927, Hawkins returned to Rolla, MO to teach physical education at the local high school, where she also began teaching dance and choreographing for local recitals and pageants. She eventually left Missouri for New York City in 1931 to work on a Master's degree at Columbia University's prestigious Teachers College. Hawkins received her degree from Columbia in 1932 and remained in New York City to teach physical education and dance at the YWCA, while also participating in the developing but vibrant modern dance scene of downtown New York.
In 1938 she moved to Chicago to begin teaching at George Williams College teaching physical education and dance courses, while also helping to build a large national community of university educators to support modern dance. In the late 1940s, during her tenure at George Williams College, she began to spend her summers in New York to work on her PhD at the Columbia Teachers College. Her doctoral research focused on the integration of dance in physical education programs and the function of modern dance in university education, and, by 1952, she received her PhD.
Her growing reputation as a national figure in dance and physical education led to her being recruited to join the faculty of the UCLA Physical Education Department in 1953. Collaborating with a number of other dance faculty within the Physical Education Department, Hawkins oversaw the development of a dance major in the department. This eventually paved the way for a split in the department between dance and physical education, which was encouraged by the university, culminating in the institution of dance as an autonomous department, replete with its own graduate program, in 1962. Hawkins chaired and taught in the newly formed UCLA Dance Department until her retirement in 1977.
During her tenure at UCLA, Hawkins also served as a dance therapist and researcher at the UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute from 1960-1977, making a number of dance therapy films, while also finding time to form the Council of Dance Administrators, a national organization that created the guidelines and standards for national dance accreditation.
Upon Hawkins' retirement from UCLA, she taught as a distinguished professor at Santa Monica College until 1987. Over the course of her career, Hawkins authored four books including Modern Dance in Higher Education (1953), Creating through Dance (1963), Dance – A Projection for the Future (1968), and Moving from Within (1991). Hawkins died in her Santa Monica home in 1998.
Scope and Content
This collection includes the professional and personal files of Alma Hawkins, the creator and original chair of the UCLA Dance Department, the nation's first autonomous university department dedicated to the discipline of Dance. Significant topics represented in the collection are papers documenting the creation of the UCLA Dance Department; national and local articles profiling Hawkins and the UCLA Dance Department; Hawkins' work with the Council of Dance Administrators, in establishing guidelines and curricula for university dance program accreditation; published and unpublished manuscripts, articles, conference papers, and speeches; research and evaluations from her work at the UCLA Neuropsychiatric Institute; and personal ephemera from her youth, including items from her time at Columbia Teachers College, University of Missouri, and photos from her time at the Bennington College summer program for modern dance, which feature Doris Humphrey, Charles Weidman, Martha Graham, Hanya Holm, and John Martin. Materials in the collection are largely textual, comprising notes, articles, agendas, publications, correspondences, memos, publications, and books. Among other formats scattered throughout the collection are photographs, videocassettes (Beta and VHS), audiocassettes, and artifacts, such as plaques and awards.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series. In many cases, original folder titles have been kept.
Series 1: Administrative (1926-1998)
Series 2: Writings (1930-1995)
Series 3: Teaching (1935-1993)
Series 4: Dance Therapy (1964-1997)
Series 5: Personal (1919-1998)
- Series 1: Administrative records, 1926-1998
  Scope and Content
  This series is focused on Hawkins' career as a Dance administrator, primarily in her capacity as Chair of the UCLA Dance Department (1953-1977), and as a faculty member and administrator responsible for helping to establish and develop the UCLA Dance Department as it separated from the UCLA Physical Education Department. The files include documents, conference programs, and correspondences related to Hawkins' leadership and membership in the Council of Dance Administrators (CODA), a national organization of dance department administrators from colleges and universities across the United States and Canada. Included here too are CODA's early guidelines and curricula for dance departments and dance programs seeking accreditation. This series are is also comprised of documents and research notes related to Hawkins' development of the UCLA Dance Department, from its beginning as an undergraduate major in the UCLA Physical Education Department to its culminating state as an autonomous university department. There are also minutes, directories, correspondences, and documents associated with Hawkins' tenure as chair of the UCLA Dance Department, as well as student theses that Hawkins oversaw, professional organization material, a collection of academic dance journals, and local and national articles profiling Hawkins and the UCLA Dance Department.
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Academic Journals: Dance Ethnology, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Journals: Dance Ethnology, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Journals: Dance Ethnology, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Journals: Dance Research Journal, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Academic Journals: Dance Teacher Now, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Academic Journals: Focus On Dance vol. 1, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Academic Journals: Focus On Dance vol. 2, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Academic Journals: Focus On Dance vol. 3-5, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Academic Journals: Impulse, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Academic Journals: Impulse, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Academic Journals: Impulse, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Academic Journals: Impulse, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Academic Journals: Impulse, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Academic Journals: Journal of Dance at UCLA, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Academic Journals: Noetic Sciences Review, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - American Academy of Physical Education, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (1 of 8), 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (2 of 8), 1970-1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (3 of 8), 1960-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (4 of 8), 1972-1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (5 of 8), 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (6 of 8), 1964-1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (7 of 8), 1979-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Articles About Hawkins and UCLA Dance (8 of 8), 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1966 (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1966 (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Conferences 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Constitution, Undated-1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Curriculum, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Financial Reports, 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Letters of Appreciation, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Letters of Appreciation, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Letters of Appreciation 1968 (1 of 2) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Letters of Appreciation 1968 (2 of 2) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Membership, 1968-1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Photos, 1986-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Project on Standards, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Publications, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Research, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Council of Dance Administrators: Speeches and Presentations, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Central Midwest Education Laboratory, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Unknown, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Development Research, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Curriculum Vitae (1 of 2), Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum Vitae (2 of 2), Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Hong Kong International Dance Conference, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Lecture Demonstrations and Concerts, 1957-1963 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Letterhead, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Magazines: The Dance Magazine, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Magazines: Time, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Marian Chace Memorial Fund, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Schools of Dance: Correspondence, 1977-1991 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - National Association of Schools of Dance: Handbooks, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - National Association of Schools of Dance: Speeches and Presentations, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - National Association of Schools of Dance: Presentations, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Professional Competency Materials, 1957-1962 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Professional Service Outside of UCLA, 1965-1984 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Student Theses UCLA (1 of 5), 1986 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Student Theses UCLA (2 of 5), 1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Student Theses UCLA (3 of 5), 1976 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Student Theses UCLA (4 of 5), 1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Student Theses UCLA (5 of 5), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - UCLA: Annual Report, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - UCLA: Staff and Faculty Directory (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Book Donations, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Correspondences, 1955-1972 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Directory, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Faculty Meetings, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Graduate Curriculum, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Graduate Program Fundraising, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Hiring Documents, 1953-1967 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Retirement Documents, 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - UCLA Dance Department: Retreat, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - UCLA Department of Physical Education: Dance Major, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Series 2: Writings, 1930-1995
  This series consists of Hawkins' writings, both published and unpublished. Included are copies, manuscripts, and drafts from her books--Modern Dance in Higher Education (1954), Creating through Dance (1964), Moving from Within (1991)--and her oral history Creating the UCLA Dance Department (1985). The series also includes research and source material notes, conference papers, and journal articles written by Hawkins, as well as speeches she delivered at various events and meetings.
  - Books: Creating the UCLA Dance Department (1 of 2), 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Books: Creating the UCLA Dance Department (2 of 2), 1985 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Books: Creating Through Dance (1 of 3), 1964 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Books: Creating Through Dance (2 of 3), 1964 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Books: Creating Through Dance (3 of 3), 1964 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Books: Modern Dance in Higher Education (1 of 3), 1954 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Books: Modern Dance in Higher Education (2 of 3), 1982 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Books: Modern Dance in Higher Education (3 of 3), 1982 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - A Biographical Sketch, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - An Experimental Approach to Choreography, 1980-1981 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1958-1961 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Columbia University Papers (1 of 2), 1949 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University Papers (2 of 2), 1949 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Conference Papers (1 of 2), 1967-1985 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Conference Papers (2 of 2), 1976-1989 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Contracts and Sales: Creating Through Dance, 1987-1995 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Contracts and Sales: Creating Through Dance, 1963-1987 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Contracts and Sales: Modern Dance in Higher Education, 1957-1965 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Contracts and Sales: Moving From Within, 1990-1995 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Contracts and Sales: Oral History Book, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Creating Through Dance: Publication Illustrations, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Dance Accompanist-Composer in University Training, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Developing Democratic Human Relations: Methods Essay, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Floppy Disk, 1995 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - How to Keep Fit Manual For Civilians, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Interviews, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts: The Intuitive Process in Dance, Undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Manuscripts: Moving From Within (1 of 3), undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Manuscripts: Moving From Within (2 of 3), undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts: Moving From Within (3 of 3), undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Moving From Within: Publication Photos, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Need for Dance Research, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Notes and Quotes, Undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oral History: Notes and Sources, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Physical Education for High School Students, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - TV camera for Dance Education, 1961-1962 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Research Projects and Creative Work, 1955-1963 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Research and Sources: Art Healing, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Research and Sources:Creative America, 1956-1967 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Research and Sources:Creativity, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Research and Sources: Creativity Form, Undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Research and Sources: Developments in Dance Education, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Research and Sources: Image Making, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Research and Sources: Modern Dance History, 1930-1962 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Research and Sources: Movement Analysis, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Research and Sources: Notes and Quotations, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Research and Sources: Physical Education, undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Research and Sources: Quotations, 1982-1986 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Research and Sources: Whitehouse and Skinner, undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Rhythmic Gymnastics, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Speeches: American Dance Therapy Association Conference, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Speeches: Aspen 1976 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Speeches: Colorado Dance Conference, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Speeches: Creative Arts Therapies Conference, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Speeches: Dance Education Forum, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Speeches: Dance Therapy, 1966-1980 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Speeches: Dance Therapy, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Speeches: Santa Monica College Lecture, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Speeches: Varied 1967-1993 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Student Quotations Used in Hawkins' Books, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Symposium on Health and Recreation: Outdoor Sports Essay, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Teaching Modern Dance, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
- Series 3: Teaching files, 1935-1993
  This series is comprised almost exclusively of hand-written discussion and lecture notes from various classes Hawkins taught in the UCLA Dance Department. Included too are syllabi, bibliographies, and some research notes for her courses. These courses pertain to dance teaching preparation, dance administration, dance history, dance therapy, dance composition, creativity, and current trends in modern dance. This series also includes a small selection of photographs, documents, and other paraphernalia from her tenure at George Williams College in Chicago and as a professor emerita at Santa Monica College.
  - Abstracts: Creativity and Foundational Knowledge, Undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Accompaniment: Music Scores, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Accompaniment: Music Scores, 1935-1947 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Aesthetic Model, 1969-1970 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Bibliographies, 1969-1973 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Choreography and Composition, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Courses Developed at UCLA, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Dance History Diagram, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Dance Therapy: Bibliography, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Dance Therapy: Class Roster, 1963-1978 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Dance Therapy: Curriculum, 1975-1978 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Dance Therapy: Summer Session, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - George Williams College: Bulletin, 1938 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - George Williams College: Dance Photos, undated (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - George Williams College: Miscellaneous, 1941-1982 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Students, 1967-1984 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1973-1988 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Support for Distinguished Teaching, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Movement and the Imaginative Process, 1982 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Movement Observation Guidelines, 1977 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Notes: Aesthetics, 1973-1978 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Notes: Aesthetic Education in Dance, 1968-1970 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Notes: Body-Self, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Notes: Creativity, undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Notes: Creativity, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Notes: Dance 158, 1955-1973 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Notes: Dance Administration Policy, 1971-1976 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Notes: Dance Education (1 of 2), undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Notes: Dance Education (2 of 2), undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Notes: Dance Lab, 1976 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Notes: Dance rehabilitation, 1967-1976 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Notes: Experiencing, 1973-1976 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Notes: Expressing, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Notes: Dance History, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Notes: Mobility Patterns, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Notes: Point of View, 1970-1976 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Notes: Relaxation, 1973-1976 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Notes: Scene Today, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Notes:Theoretical Model, 1969-1973 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Research: Choreography, undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Santa Monica College: Book List, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Santa Monica College: Choreography Notes, 1993 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Santa Monica College: Dance 48 Notes, 1985-1986 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Santa Monica College: Dance Classes, 1984-1985 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Santa Monica College: Distinguished Scholar Press Release, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Santa Monica College: Fundamentals of Choreography, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Santa Monica College:Lecture Notes, 1979-1985 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Santa Monica College: Mentoring Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Santa Monica College: Mentor Program in the Arts, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Santa Monica College: Photos, undated (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Santa Monica College: Research Grant, 1979-1981 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Santa Monica College: Student Journals, 1984-1985 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Santa Monica College: Teaching Credential, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Santa Monica College: Teaching Evaluation, 1983 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Scholarly Writing Guidelines, 1978 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Student Comments, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - UCLA Teaching Contracts, 1954-1962 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - UCLA Dance 227, 1967-1974 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - UCLA Course Syllabi, undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - UCLA Course Descriptions, 1970-1971 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - UCLA Course Dance 158A, undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - UCLA Dance Therapy Class Photos, undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - UCLA Extension, 1959 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - UCLA Student Publications, 1968-1969 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - UCLA Material for Promotion, 1957 (Box 23, Folder 14)
- Series 4: Dance therapy, 1964-1997
  This series pertains to Hawkins' role as a practicing dance therapist and includes documents and clinical evaluations relating to her work at the UCLA's Neuropsychiatric Institute. Also included are notes, scripts, documentation, and photos from Hawkins' films about dance therapy. Lastly, the series contains writings, research, documents of certification, and conference material from her membership in the American Dance Therapy Association, as well as copies from Hawkins' collection of the American Journal of Dance Therapy.
  - American Dance Therapy Association: Conferences, 1971 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - American Dance Therapy Association: Early Writings, 1989 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - American Dance Therapy Association: Membership, 1995-1997 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - American Dance Therapy Association: Southern California Luncheon Honor, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - American Journal of Dance Therapy, 1991-1993 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - American Journal of Dance Therapy, 1994-1997 (Box 24, Folder 7)